<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
 <title type="text">logc io: logc io</title>
 <link rel="self" href="http://logc.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" />
 <link href="http://logc.github.io/index.html" />
 <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-index-html</id>
 <updated>2016-09-23T19:48:27Z</updated>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Racket and vim-syntastic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2016/09/23/racket-and-vim-syntastic/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2016-09-23-racket-and-vim-syntastic</id>
  <published>2016-09-23T19:48:27Z</published>
  <updated>2016-09-23T19:48:27Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current Syntastic checker for Racket syntax in Vim is the &lt;code&gt;racket&lt;/code&gt; executable itself. This means that the current buffer is executed by Racket whenever it is checked for syntax, and this can have unintended consequences, e.g. entering an infinite loop, if you happen to open the wrong file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to just get the syntax errors, add this to your &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;let g:syntastic_racket_racket_args="--load"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Binaries and customers</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2016/02/26/binaries-and-customers/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2016-02-26-binaries-and-customers</id>
  <published>2016-02-26T22:54:28Z</published>
  <updated>2016-02-26T22:54:28Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just this week I realised that the barrier between binaries and source code is the same barrier that there is between a customer and a collaborator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A customer is someone who wants to use your product and does not care about its inner workings: he is prepared to give you money in exchange for both things (using your product, and not having to know how it works).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A collaborator is someone that works with you in creating the very same product that you intend to sell later on. His interests are exactly the opposite as those of the customer: a collaborator does not necessarily need to use the product, and he needs to know as much as possible about your product in order to contribute as much as possible to it. Otherwise, the collaboration will be wasteful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, you should give to your customer a binary (the end-result of your software), and you should give to your collborator a source code representation of your product (a textual representation of the same software).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to realize this while discussing during a technical speech with one of our tech leads. He was promoting the use of a tool that allowed designers to turn specifications into wireframes, and those wireframes into workable code. He expected this tool to avoid that designers and developers communicated &amp;ldquo;via screenshots&amp;rdquo;. I agreed with him, and said that we needed specification owners to work as close to the code as possible, because the ultimate specification of a feature is the source code itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point, he disagreed with me, and said that he did not expect designers to &amp;ldquo;actually code&amp;rdquo;. I said anything that was not a textual representation of the result was wasteful, since the receivers of a binary representation would have to reverse engineer how that binary was created. With &amp;ldquo;binary&amp;rdquo; I meant the screenshots, but also other representations like videos, presentations, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He contended that why should a designer treat you (the lowly coder) as anything different than a customer. And at that point it suddenly dawned on me: because the customer pays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The money transaction marks the frontier between one organization and another, and it also marks this curious effect: the customer is &lt;strong&gt;entitled&lt;/strong&gt; to a &lt;strong&gt;less complex&lt;/strong&gt; representation of the product, precisely because the customer/provider relationship is a hallmark of the division of labour, and in plain words it means &amp;ldquo;I have other shit to do, just give me the plain result of your work &amp;amp; don&amp;rsquo;t bother me with details.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">The difference between Racket and Haskell</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2015/10/16/the-difference-between-racket-and-haskell/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2015-10-16-the-difference-between-racket-and-haskell</id>
  <published>2015-10-16T13:10:42Z</published>
  <updated>2015-10-16T13:10:42Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During most of 2014, and previous years, I was very fond of Haskell and learnt the basics of developing server applications with it. I was captured by the elegance and expresiveness of the language. I was specifically enthusiastic about the possibility to write multithreaded and type-safe code without all the fuss of C++ or Java. But I was let down by the complexity of &lt;code&gt;cabal&lt;/code&gt; and the seeming inability of the Haskell community to provide stable packages that would compile on different platforms. I mean actually compile, not just promise that they will compile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the end of 2014, I got word of Racket as a modern Scheme (Scheme, in turn, being the moder Lisp). For a long time, I had kept in my ever-expanding to-do list to learn a bit of Lisp. People told me that, if I should start anywhere in that &amp;ldquo;language space&amp;rdquo;, I should probably start with Racket, so I gave it a go. Here is a list of the differences I have felt between both languages, not exactly from the point of view of abstract language features but from the point of view of pragmatic work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Racket packages just work&lt;/strong&gt;. I know that &lt;code&gt;cabal&lt;/code&gt; problems have been already  &lt;a href="https://www.fpcomplete.com/blog/2015/05/thousand-user-haskell-survey"&gt;identified by the Haskell  community&lt;/a&gt;  as a pain point (not to say a pain in the &amp;hellip;). But I cannot stress enough how  frustrating it can be to read &lt;a href="http://haskell.cs.yale.edu/euterpea/"&gt;the wonderful documentation about a music  library&lt;/a&gt; which is &lt;a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/Euterpea"&gt;listed in  Hackage&lt;/a&gt;, try to build it and  fail completely. Or develop a &lt;a href="http://www.yesodweb.com"&gt;Yesod application&lt;/a&gt; and  being unable to pin down all the sub-dependencies of dependencies, so that a  build in my development machine would succeed and on the machine of my  co-worker it would not, even with the same operating system and GHCi version.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The rest of tooling is wonderful&lt;/strong&gt;. How is it possible that there is a full  IDE for Racket, including plugins developed by third parties, and the only  IDE for Haskell that I am aware of is the &amp;ldquo;IDE in the cloud&amp;rdquo; from FPComplete?  OK, it seems there is a project called Leksah that builds an IDE for Haskell in  Haskell. It comes in fourth place in the &lt;a href="https://wiki.haskell.org/IDEs"&gt;IDEs page of the Haskell  wiki&lt;/a&gt;, after a &amp;ldquo;colorer plugin for Eclipse&amp;rdquo;.  Which, to me, means that the Haskell community is not serious about giving  people the means to learn Haskell: even if I am the kind of developer that  prefers a simple text editor and a shell, when learning a new language I might  need some more help to &amp;ldquo;keep things stable&amp;rdquo; until I have a better grasp on the  language. With Racket, usually I develop on Vim and the Racket REPL, but when I  am in doubt about a problem, I fire up DrRacket and follow its wise advice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; But it does not stop at the IDE. &lt;code&gt;raco&lt;/code&gt; is a much better tool at handling  packages, documentation and almost all development tasks than &lt;code&gt;cabal&lt;/code&gt; will ever  be. Maybe &lt;code&gt;stack&lt;/code&gt; will get there at some point. However, and I hate to use this  argumentation, &lt;code&gt;raco&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;strong&gt;already there, bundled with Racket just like the  IDE, and is used by the whole community&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;code&gt;stack&lt;/code&gt; has been in development just  four months at the time of this writing, and it has yet to prove that it is  adopted by the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The syntax is terse and this is because the community is not out to show  off&lt;/strong&gt;. This is quite a subjective point, but hey, this is my blog. I do not  remember which author famously remarked that &amp;ldquo;software organizations tend to  write software that reflects the mental state of the organization&amp;rdquo;. Whenever  reading up on Haskell, I noticed a &amp;ldquo;climbing&amp;rdquo; feeling: any concept already  covered was only a step in an infinite ladder of abstractions. At first, you  imagine that from some point on you will be able to write &amp;ldquo;good enough&amp;rdquo; Haskell  to tackle at least the lowly tasks that you intend to accomplish. But this is  never the case. There is yet another language extension that does what you  want, if only you had learnt about it before. In my opinion, this reflects the  elite thinking of (at least a part of) the Haskell community. Nothing is ever  clever enough: there must be a new way to define Arrows, Lenses, and Barbed  wires to fool those who have dared to understand Monads.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Contrast this with the simplicity of the Racket syntax, which is a very  intentional heritage from Scheme and Lisp. There is almost nothing to learn.  From around half of the Racket guide you can write Racket programs that work.  The whole language is there to be expanded by you, if you do not find its  features enough. Yes, there are &amp;ldquo;different languages&amp;rdquo; that can be thought of as  equivalent to the &amp;ldquo;language extensions&amp;rdquo; of Haskell, but when did you read on  any Haskell manual how to introduce your own language extensions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;If you are thinking, &amp;ldquo;oh but Haskell is typed, while Racket is interpreted&amp;rdquo;,  please have a look at  &lt;a href="http://docs.racket-lang.org/guide/contracts.html"&gt;contracts&lt;/a&gt; for the safety,  and at &lt;a href="http://docs.racket-lang.org/ts-guide/index.html"&gt;Typed Racket&lt;/a&gt; for the  performance. Again the day is saved for Racket (yay).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is enough ranting. I would really like to see the Haskell language improve and deliver on the promise that it once was, at least for me. Until then, I will be happily writing parenthesis in Racket.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Open files from last commit in Vim</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2015/07/15/open-files-from-last-commit-in-vim/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2015-07-15-open-files-from-last-commit-in-vim</id>
  <published>2015-07-15T11:05:47Z</published>
  <updated>2015-07-15T11:05:47Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is always a nuisance to remember which files were you working on when you last exited your editing session. I have tried different approaches, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;leaving a test that does not succeed in order to get an errortrace that  points to the next task I should tackle&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;opening the editor inside a &lt;code&gt;tmux&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;screen&lt;/code&gt; session, and therefore never  ending the editing session&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last idea I had was to create a unfinished Git commit (called &amp;ldquo;Unfinished: The commit title&amp;rdquo;), and use Git to retrieve the name of the files that were touched in that commit. You can do it like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git log --pretty=format: --name-only -n 1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you alias that command in your &lt;code&gt;.gitconfig&lt;/code&gt;, e.g. to &lt;code&gt;lastedited&lt;/code&gt;, you can then open the files in your editor by command subtitution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ vim $(git lastedited)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">If programming languages were music genres</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2015/02/27/if-programming-languages-were-music-genres/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2015-02-27-if-programming-languages-were-music-genres</id>
  <published>2015-02-27T16:52:41Z</published>
  <updated>2015-02-27T16:52:41Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are quite some posts out there that compare programming languages to something else, like religions, rock bands, types of women &amp;hellip; There is a &lt;a href="http://lambda-the-ultimate.org/node/3133"&gt;compilation of these over at Lambda the Ultimate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One comparison that I find missing is that of programming languages to music genres (maybe the &amp;ldquo;Subcultures&amp;rdquo; post was simmilar, but it seems to be a dead link now). This is the more surprising since it looks like developers tend to argue about their favourite languages just like most people about music: everyone knows it is a highly subjective preference, but no-one escapes trying to convince others that they are not listening to the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here is my (completely subjective) view on programming languages as music genres:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C: punk rock&lt;/strong&gt; It only has three chords, it was born in the late 70&amp;rsquo;s, and,  despite several reports to the contrary, it is not dead yet.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;C++: heavy metal&lt;/strong&gt; It claims to be similar but more technical than C, it is  subdivided in dozens of different subgenres that you will never totally  master, and despite the whole technical allure, at some point you start  thinking it is a bit commercial and superficial.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Java: techno&lt;/strong&gt; No one likes it really, but peer pressure drives you at some  point to go to a place where they are playing it loudly, and you have to do  as if you enjoy it.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Python: blues rock&lt;/strong&gt; It does what C does, but slower and with one and two  more chords thrown here and there. Everyone likes it for a while, but then,  after some hours of listening to it, you start wondering if there is something  else.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruby: reggae&lt;/strong&gt; Coming from an exotic place, it has gained mainstream  acceptance, it is as slow as Python, and people in that scene tend to regard  themselves as cool without further explanation.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LISP: classical music&lt;/strong&gt; Someone in a position of authority told you long  ago to learn its basics because it was important for your education, you  thought at the time that it was a hateful and obsolete past-time, but as time  goes by, you go back to it and find comfort in its beauty.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Haskell: mathcore&lt;/strong&gt; Not everyone knows it, and those who do think they are  some kind of elite. It is 100% faster and more complex than anything else  out there. It is several layers of purity removed from C, although they  share some distant roots.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erlang: world music&lt;/strong&gt; A lot of different musical styles thrown together and  whose unifying trait seems to be that, apparently, very few people listen to  them.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clojure: hip hop&lt;/strong&gt; The base is made with the same tools as techno, but with  old soul records played on top. Who would have thought that those sweet  performers from Motown sounded so aggresive when played with a bad attitude?&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scala: rap rock&lt;/strong&gt; It tries to bring together the best of two worlds and it  largely succeeds. The hardcore fans of each camp will deny there is any need  to blend their styles together, but from time to time find themselves  listening to it and nodding.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Python egg tagged with Git commit hash</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2014/04/01/python-egg-tagged-with-git-commit-hash/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2014-04-01-python-egg-tagged-with-git-commit-hash</id>
  <published>2014-04-01T15:22:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-04-01T15:22:00Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;h2 id="svn"&gt;SVN&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Python&amp;rsquo;s setuptools provide a simple mechanism to tag your built distributions with the SVN revision they belong to, by creating a &lt;code&gt;setup.cfg&lt;/code&gt; file along the normal &lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt;, and there write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[egg_info]
# Add svn revision to the file name
tag_svn_revision = 1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id="git"&gt;Git&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to do the same for Git? Or in general, with other information? (Date tagging is also supported by default).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: modify directly the &lt;code&gt;options&lt;/code&gt; dictionary in the call to &lt;code&gt;setup&lt;/code&gt;, in &lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt;. There, you can put anything you can compute with Python or system calls. E.g. for git:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: python"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;shlex&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;subprocess&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;check_output&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;GIT_HEAD_REV&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;check_output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;shlex&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;git rev-parse --short HEAD&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;strip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# ... other keys like project name, version, etc ...&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;options&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;egg_info&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tag_build&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"dev_"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;GIT_HEAD_REV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)),&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that setup, distributions (&lt;code&gt;sdist&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;bdist&lt;/code&gt;) would be tagged with the string &amp;ldquo;dev&amp;rdquo; and the git hash of the latest commit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; bin/python setup.py sdist bdist_egg
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ls dist
&lt;span class="go"&gt;pyhello-0.1dev-92ffa06.tar.gz    pyhello-0.1dev_92ffa06-py2.7.egg&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever you want to build a stable release (without any &amp;ldquo;dev&amp;rdquo; tags), just set the key to empty in your &lt;code&gt;setup.cfg&lt;/code&gt;, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[egg_info]
tag_build =&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Wordcount in C++</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2014/01/21/wordcount-in-c/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2014-01-21-wordcount-in-c</id>
  <published>2014-01-21T14:52:26Z</published>
  <updated>2014-01-21T14:52:26Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the standard example for MapReduce applications, counting the words in a file. Note that this snippet is not threaded nor distributed. It is just a curiosity: how to implement the same in C++, using the STL to avoid having any &lt;code&gt;for&lt;/code&gt; loop!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: c++"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;fstream&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;numeric&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;sstream&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;vector&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;istringstream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;istream_iterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;split_at_whitespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;istringstream&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;iss&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;istream_iterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;iss&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;istream_iterator&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{}};&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;split_at_whitespace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current_outputs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;transform&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;tokens&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current_outputs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;make_pair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current_outputs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reduce&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;outputs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;accumulate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;outputs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;outputs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;second&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="p"&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;argc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;argv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;argc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Usage: "&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;argv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;" infile"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;endl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;argv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;];&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ifstream&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;infile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;pair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;occurences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;getline&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;infile&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;auto&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line_occurences&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;occurences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;occurences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line_occurences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line_occurences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;());&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reduce&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;occurences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"File "&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;filename&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;" holds "&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;" words"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;endl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compile and run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; cat &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; EOF &amp;gt; sample.txt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt; This is a first line&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt; This is a second line&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt; EOF&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; c++ main.cpp -o wordcount -std&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;c++11 &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; ./wordcount sample.txt
&lt;span class="go"&gt;File sample.txt holds 10 words&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Reduce in standard C++</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2014/01/20/reduce-in-standard-c/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2014-01-20-reduce-in-standard-c</id>
  <published>2014-01-20T13:47:25Z</published>
  <updated>2014-01-20T13:47:25Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;h2 id="accumulate-instead-of-loop"&gt;Accumulate instead of loop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can traverse a C++ vector in many ways. Looping over a counter variable that goes from 0 to the vector size or taking an iterator from the vector&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;begin&lt;/code&gt; to its &lt;code&gt;end&lt;/code&gt; pointer positions are well-known ways to access its elements. When you are collapsing the elements into a single accumulator value (an operation usually called &lt;code&gt;reduce&lt;/code&gt; in functional programming), you can use the &lt;code&gt;std::accumulate&lt;/code&gt; function in the &lt;code&gt;numeric&lt;/code&gt; header.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: c++"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;iostream&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;vector&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="cp"&gt;#include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cpf"&gt;&amp;lt;numeric&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cp"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cell&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;probability&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kt"&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;vector&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;grid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;size_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;cell&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;probability&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;};&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;grid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;push_back&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;accumulate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;grid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;begin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;grid&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cell&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;probability&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;});&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;std&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;cout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="compile-and-run"&gt;Compile and run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, the compilation needs a &lt;code&gt;-std=c++11&lt;/code&gt; flag in order to set the standard to C++11, a fairly recent standard that is not supported by all compilers and systems. However, the part that is written in this new standard is the &lt;em&gt;accumulating function&lt;/em&gt;, which is expressed as a lambda in this example. If you move its code to a named function outside the &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt;, this code should compile with many more compilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; c++ main.cpp -o example -std&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;c++11 &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; ./example
&lt;span class="go"&gt;0.3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">How do you develop with Yesod</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/how-do-you-develop-with-yesod/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2013-12-04-how-do-you-develop-with-yesod</id>
  <published>2013-12-04T14:39:03Z</published>
  <updated>2013-12-04T14:39:03Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesod tutorials and examples can be found on the &lt;a href="http://www.yesodweb.com/book"&gt;Yesod book&lt;/a&gt;, which is freely available online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, many of the examples given are self-contained (which means that handler functions, data models and templates are defined in a single module, where a Warp web server is started as well). There is &lt;a href="http://www.yesodweb.com/book/scaffolding-and-the-site-template"&gt;a chapter that describes the scaffolded template&lt;/a&gt;, i.e. what you get after you start with Yesod, but it is rather a description of its advantages and structure, not so much a detailed how-to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this post is to explain to a new Yesod developer &amp;ldquo;What do I do after &amp;hellip; ?&amp;rdquo; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; yesod init
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly summarized, what you need after this command is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Describe the &lt;strong&gt;data models&lt;/strong&gt; your Web application is going to store persistently&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Describe which &lt;strong&gt;routes&lt;/strong&gt; are going to exist in your Web application&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Write the &lt;strong&gt;handler functions&lt;/strong&gt; that answer requests to those routes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Write the &lt;strong&gt;Hamlet templates&lt;/strong&gt; that are filled out by the handler functions (and  possibly Lucius and Julius templates)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;yesod add-handler&lt;/code&gt; command automates the process of adding &lt;strong&gt;routes&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;handler functions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="adding-data-models"&gt;Adding data models&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new data model has to be described in the &lt;code&gt;config/models&lt;/code&gt; text file. With &amp;ldquo;text file&amp;rdquo; we mean that you write in &amp;ldquo;near free&amp;rdquo; syntax, but nevertheless many of the keywords are Haskell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="basics"&gt;Basics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new model consists of a name and a description of its fields. The description of fields consists, in turn, of a name and a type for the field. The type can be &lt;code&gt;Int&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Text&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;UTCTime&lt;/code&gt;, or other Haskell types. The type can also be qualified with a Monad (usually &lt;code&gt;Maybe&lt;/code&gt;) and have a defaul value. Let&amp;rsquo;s see a simple example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Book
    title Text
    author Text
    publisher Text Maybe
    published UTCTime default=CURRENT_TIME&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An identifier field is &lt;strong&gt;automatically added&lt;/strong&gt; to each model. The name of that field is always &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;modelName&amp;gt;Id&lt;/code&gt;, e.g. for the previous model it would be &lt;code&gt;BookId&lt;/code&gt;. This is a unique identifier stored in the database using the database mechanisms if available, or the Persistent module&amp;rsquo;s mechanisms otherwise. We usually do not need to care about &lt;strong&gt;writing&lt;/strong&gt; this ID, but we will be interested in &lt;strong&gt;reading&lt;/strong&gt; it from the database, as we will see later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing we get for free are &lt;strong&gt;accessor functions&lt;/strong&gt; for each field. These are called &lt;code&gt;bookTitle&lt;/code&gt; to get the title, &lt;code&gt;bookAuthor&lt;/code&gt; to get the author, and so on&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the mentioned, you can create your own models. Let&amp;rsquo;s review other features that are slightly more advanced but almost unavoidable in any app that is not completely trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="reference-other-models"&gt;Reference other models&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;strong&gt;reference field in other models&lt;/strong&gt;. This creates &lt;em&gt;foreign keys&lt;/em&gt; in relational databases, or is managed by Persistent otherwise. You refer to the other model with an uppercase and join the name of model and field in camel case. An example is in the default models written by the scaffolding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;User
    ...
Email
    user UserId Maybe&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also an example of using the automatically created field &lt;code&gt;UserId&lt;/code&gt; for the User.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="declare-records-to-be-unique"&gt;Declare records to be unique&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;strong&gt;declare records to be unique with respect to a field&lt;/strong&gt;. The unique ID are handed out to anything new in the store otherwise. You can specify that a record has to have a new value in one of its fields to be accepted. Again the default models provide an example of this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;User
    ident Text
    UniqueUser ident&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id="derive-typeclasses"&gt;Derive typeclasses&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as a last note, you can directly &lt;strong&gt;declare your models to derive Haskell typeclasses&lt;/strong&gt; e.g. Eq, Ord, Show. Which means the model, when loaded from database and available to be manipulated, will have the correct functions of that typeclass already implemented. ( In the case of Eq, it will be equatable, in the case of Ord, it will be comparable, and in the case of Show it will be printable; this, of course, in the case the compiler can deduce out of the fields composing the model how to implement such functions for you ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of deriving typeclasses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Person
    ...
    deriving (Show)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id="adding-routes"&gt;Adding routes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You declare new routes to be answered to in the &lt;code&gt;config/routes&lt;/code&gt; text file. This can be automated with the &lt;code&gt;yesod add-handler&lt;/code&gt; command. However, let&amp;rsquo;s review it to gain a bit of control on the underlying machinery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new route starts from the root &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; and lists a &lt;em&gt;resource name&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;query parameters&lt;/em&gt;. After that there is a space, and the name of the handler function(s) that handle requests to that particular route. Again a space, and a space-separated list of HTTP methods that are allowed on that route. An example with all of these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/book/#BookId BookR GET PUT DELETE&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;book&lt;/code&gt; is the &lt;em&gt;resource name&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;code&gt;#BookId&lt;/code&gt; is the &lt;em&gt;query parameter&lt;/em&gt;, BookR is the shared part of the name of the &lt;em&gt;handler functions&lt;/em&gt;, and the allowed methods are GET, PUT and DELETE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We say &lt;code&gt;BookR&lt;/code&gt; is the shared part of the name because a single handler function is expected &lt;strong&gt;for each one of the allowed methods&lt;/strong&gt;. That is, in the above example, &lt;code&gt;getBookR&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;putBookR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deleteBookR&lt;/code&gt; are expected to exist somewhere (probably in a module called &lt;code&gt;Book&lt;/code&gt; within the &lt;code&gt;Handlers&lt;/code&gt; directory).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually the convention for a REST API is that GET allows to see an instance of a model, POST allows to create an instance of a model, PUT allows to modify an instance of a model, and DELETE allows to, well, delete it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you have added a new route, the application will not compile until there are handler functions for all of the new resources and allowed methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="adding-handler-functions"&gt;Adding handler functions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You add new functions to handle requests in modules under the &lt;code&gt;Handler&lt;/code&gt; directory. This can be automated with the &lt;code&gt;yesod add-handler&lt;/code&gt; command. However, let&amp;rsquo;s review it to gain a bit of control on the underlying machinery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A handler function must exist &lt;strong&gt;for each resource and for each allowed HTTP method on that resource&lt;/strong&gt;. That means if we declared the resource &lt;code&gt;/donkey&lt;/code&gt; to accept requests with GET, POST and DELETE methods, then we have to implement &lt;code&gt;getDonkeyR&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;postDonkeyR&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deleteDonkeyR&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; means &amp;ldquo;resource&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us see a stub example of one of those functions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: haskell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;getDonkeyR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;DonkeyId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Handler&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Html&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nf"&gt;getDonkeyR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;donkeyId&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;undefined&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id="handler-function-signature"&gt;Handler function signature&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a Haskell function, the function signature is important to understand what the function does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of Yesod, the &lt;strong&gt;input to the function are query parameters&lt;/strong&gt;, which are typed to correspond to model fields. That is, you do not get an integer, but a &lt;code&gt;DonkeyId&lt;/code&gt; &amp;mdash; if you specified in the route that the &lt;code&gt;donkey&lt;/code&gt; resource has a query parameter of that type. This helps ensure that there are no typos in the &lt;code&gt;routes&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;models&lt;/code&gt; text files that cause your app to fail on deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;output of the function&lt;/strong&gt; is quite determined by Yesod, so it is easy to read, but you have to accept that the framework &amp;ldquo;knows what it is doing&amp;rdquo;. You usually have a &lt;code&gt;Handler Html&lt;/code&gt; result type; which means that the result of your function is a function that knows how to answer a request with HTML. This function is what is going to be called by the application when it is running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do not let that make your head explode&lt;/em&gt;: it is like when you compile a function with gcc. It is not your source code that is run when the resulting binary is executed: it is the object representation of it. This is not exactly the same but for the moment, it is a good enough explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other output types for the function are &lt;code&gt;Handler RepJson&lt;/code&gt; if the function returns JSON, or even &lt;code&gt;Handler TypedContent&lt;/code&gt; if the function returns HTML or JSON depending on what the client has requested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="handler-function-body"&gt;Handler function body&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the function itself, you may want to do many different things. Let us discuss the most usual:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;getting something out of the database and into a template for viewing  ( &lt;strong&gt;Database -&amp;gt; User&lt;/strong&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;getting something out of a template form from the user, and inserting that  into the database ( &lt;strong&gt;User -&amp;gt; Database&lt;/strong&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h5 id="database---user"&gt;Database -&amp;gt; User&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: haskell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;getBooksR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Handler&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Html&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nf"&gt;getBooksR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;books&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;runDB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;selectList&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;Asc&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;BookTitle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;formWidget&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;enctype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;generateFormPost&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bookForm&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;defaultLayout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;widgetFile&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"books"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first line after &lt;code&gt;do&lt;/code&gt; allows us to get a Book model out of the database. The &lt;code&gt;runDB&lt;/code&gt; function runs any query on the database, while the &lt;code&gt;selectList&lt;/code&gt; function composes a query that returns its results as a list. The empty first argument means we take &lt;strong&gt;all fields&lt;/strong&gt; from each record, and the second argument accepts a number of filters and modifyers. The example shown is equivalent, in SQL, to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: sql"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;SELECT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;FROM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;books&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;ORDER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;BY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;"BookTitle"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;ASC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we would go on to render the correct HTML template with the default layout. The template will have direct access to the &lt;code&gt;books&lt;/code&gt; variable because it is in the same scope (the handler function). We will see how this happens when we discuss templates. The rendering happens with the line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: haskell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;defaultLayout&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;widgetFile&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"books"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The template rendering takes the &lt;code&gt;defaultLayout&lt;/code&gt; function, applied on the result of loading a widgetFile by name. The default layout renders the template found under &lt;code&gt;templates/default-layout.*&lt;/code&gt; and includes within it the result of rendering whatever is on the &lt;code&gt;templates/books.*&lt;/code&gt; files. This helps make the look and feel uniform across the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You may notice that we are skipping a line in the &lt;code&gt;getBooksR&lt;/code&gt; function, between reading from database and rendering the template. It is concerned with &lt;strong&gt;form rendering&lt;/strong&gt;, but for the sake of brevity we will not discuss it here)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id="user---database"&gt;User -&amp;gt; Database&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: haskell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;postBooksR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;::&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Handler&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;Html&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nf"&gt;postBooksR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;runFormPost&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;bookForm&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="kr"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kt"&gt;FormSuccess&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;book&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;bookid&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;runDB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;book&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;setMessage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Book registered"&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="kr"&gt;_&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;setMessage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Invalid data"&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="n"&gt;redirect&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;BooksR&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first line after &lt;code&gt;do&lt;/code&gt; gets the result out of a form that is defined and rendered elsewhere. The result may be a success, because all inputs are filled out and are of the expected types, or it may be anything else (an error), where we print an error message and do no more. If we have a success, then we can extract the specific &lt;code&gt;book&lt;/code&gt; (of type &lt;code&gt;Book&lt;/code&gt;) out of the &lt;code&gt;FormSuccess&lt;/code&gt; monad via pattern matching, and then insert it into the DB via the Persist &lt;code&gt;insert&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: haskell"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;bookid&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;runDB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;book&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice this works without any more specifications because we know, from the compile process, that the result of parsing the form contents must have enough informations to build a Book model, and a Book model can be written to database because we have already parsed it and created the necessary tables (in the case of a relational DB engine) on app startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice also we receive a bookId as a result of inserting, but we can ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="after-writing-your-handlers"&gt;After writing your handlers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After writing your handlers, you must make the application aware that they exist. Import the relevant module in in the &lt;code&gt;Application&lt;/code&gt; module, and also remember to list them in the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;application&amp;gt;.cabal&lt;/code&gt; file, under &lt;code&gt;exposed-modules&lt;/code&gt;. This makes the &lt;code&gt;cabal&lt;/code&gt; build system know that it must include the new handler files in the compilation, and the &lt;code&gt;Application&lt;/code&gt; module aware that it has to import those modules if it wants to answer the calls to some of the resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="adding-hamlet-templates"&gt;Adding Hamlet templates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We said earlier that the variables extracted from storage are rendered in the template. A template is a file that lives in the &lt;code&gt;templates&lt;/code&gt; directory and is called whatever we want the &lt;code&gt;widgetFile&lt;/code&gt; function to find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamlet is a template language that describes HTML to produce. A very short summary of Hamlet: you do not need to close HTML tags, this will be done for you. &lt;em&gt;With the important exception of links. Do not forget to close them with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the template, you can refer to any variable that is available in the handler function (because the generated code is inserted in the function code directly before the results are produced). See this example template to render a Book model:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h2&amp;gt; Book: #{bookTitle book}

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt; by #{bookAuthor book}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the template, we can use the &lt;strong&gt;accessor functions&lt;/strong&gt; we got for free out of the model definition. Remember that this is Haskell, so the function must go before the arguments. We drop into Haskell from the template by using &lt;code&gt;#{ }&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is more syntax to iterate over a collection of &lt;code&gt;books&lt;/code&gt; and control &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; we render some thing or the other depending on the presence of a variable, but we will skip this. There is Yesod documentation available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us mention another important feature of these templates: &lt;strong&gt;compiled in-site links&lt;/strong&gt;. This means you refer to other pages within your website &lt;em&gt;through their resource names&lt;/em&gt;, not through a simple string. In the homepage, for instance, you should include a link to the &amp;ldquo;books&amp;rdquo; page by using:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a href=@{BooksR}&amp;gt;Add new book&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice you use an &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt;, not the &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; symbol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes it &lt;strong&gt;impossible for you to have dead links within the site&lt;/strong&gt;. They are checked by the compiler on each site update, and the compilation will fail if there is something misspelled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="summing-up"&gt;Summing up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have reviewed what are the minimal changes you have to do to a scaffolded site in order to add a new feature to it, in some more depth than necessary since you can use &lt;code&gt;yesod add-handler&lt;/code&gt; to make many of the changes for you. However, now you should understand better what is this command doing and why could it fail. The changes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;config/models&lt;/code&gt;: describe &lt;strong&gt;data models&lt;/strong&gt; stored&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;config/routes&lt;/code&gt;: describe &lt;strong&gt;routes&lt;/strong&gt; served, as resources&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;Handler/&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;.hs&lt;/code&gt;: write &lt;strong&gt;handler functions&lt;/strong&gt; that answer requests to  those routes; include them in &lt;code&gt;Application.hs&lt;/code&gt; and list them on  &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;application&amp;gt;.cabal&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;templates/&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;.{hamlet,lucius,julius}&lt;/code&gt;: write the &lt;strong&gt;templates&lt;/strong&gt; that  are filled out by the handler functions&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Instalar Python 2.7 y NumPy sobre RedHat 6</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/instalar-python-2-7-y-numpy-sobre-redhat-6/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2013-12-04-instalar-python-2-7-y-numpy-sobre-redhat-6</id>
  <published>2013-12-04T11:44:57Z</published>
  <updated>2013-12-04T11:44:57Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RedHat y centOS tienen la fastidiosa dependencia de su gestor de paquetes, yum, con la versin 2.6 de Python desde tiempos inmemoriales. Lo que en tecnologa son unos seis o siete aos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instalar Python 2.7 no es posible con los repositorios instalados por defecto, y si tienes la mala idea de instalar un repositorio donde s est y meterlo como paquete que supedita al python por defecto, te acabas de cargar yum (y la posibilidad ms sencilla de deshacer tus cambios).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La mejor manera, pese a lo que pueda parecer, es &lt;strong&gt;instalar desde fuentes&lt;/strong&gt;, haciendo lo que se conoce como &amp;ldquo;altinstall&amp;rdquo; (instalacin alternativa). Esto crea ejecutables llamados &lt;code&gt;python2.7&lt;/code&gt; bajo &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin&lt;/code&gt;, que &lt;strong&gt;no sobreescriben&lt;/strong&gt; el comando &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; normal del sistema; ste sigue apuntando a un ejecutable bajo &lt;code&gt;/usr/bin&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; wget http://www.python.org/ftp/python/2.7.6/Python-2.7.6.tgz
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; tar xvfz Python-2.7.6.tgz
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; Python-2.7.6
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; ./configure
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; make
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; sudo make altinstall
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adems de esto, es recomendable instalar &lt;strong&gt;un &lt;code&gt;easy_install&lt;/code&gt; alternativo tambin&lt;/strong&gt;, ya que, si no, todas las libreras de python se instalarn para la 2.6 y no para la 2.7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; wget http://pypi.python.org/packages/2.7/s/setuptools/setuptools-0.6c11-py2.7.egg
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; sudo -i
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;PATH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$PATH&lt;/span&gt;:/usr/local/bin
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; sh setuptools-0.6c11-py2.7.egg
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;#&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;exit&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; sudo rm /usr/local/bin/easy_install &lt;span class="c1"&gt;## remove the symlink that shadows the system easy_install&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# You may now try the easy_install for 2.7 with e.g.:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; sudo /usr/local/bin/easy_install-2.7 numpy
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Este post es una combinacin de &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4149361/on-linux-suse-or-redhat-how-do-i-load-python-2-7"&gt;dos respuestas en Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt;, y mi propia experiencia con este mismo problema.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Unicode encodings</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2013/12/03/unicode-encodings/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2013-12-03-unicode-encodings</id>
  <published>2013-12-03T13:46:19Z</published>
  <updated>2013-12-03T13:46:19Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Por fin he entendido cul es la diferencia entre Unicode y UTF&amp;ndash;8! Y lo que es ms importante, cmo se declaran correctamente &lt;code&gt;strings&lt;/code&gt; en Unicode en Python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unicode es &lt;strong&gt;la tabla de equivalencias&lt;/strong&gt; entre caracteres de (casi) todos los lenguajes humanos, y un nmero asignado a ese caracter en concreto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UTF&amp;ndash;8 es &lt;strong&gt;la manera de comprimir&lt;/strong&gt; esos nmeros en uno o dos bytes, en lugar de usar 4 bytes por caracter, aprovechando el hecho de que la mayora de caracteres habituales estn en los nmeros bajos (menores de 128).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es decir, si el &amp;ldquo;encodificador&amp;rdquo; encuentra un nmero &amp;lt; 128, deja ese nmero; si encuentra uno mayor, pero menor de X (donde X es un lmite que no recuerdo), usa &lt;strong&gt;dos bytes&lt;/strong&gt; para expresar este nmero. El &amp;ldquo;decodificador&amp;rdquo; entonces sabe que cada caracter menor de 128 est &amp;ldquo;solo&amp;rdquo;, mientras que si encuentra uno mayor, entonces debe leer tambin el siguiente byte para tener el nmero correcto con el que ir a la tabla Unicode y obtener el caracter adecuado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Se puede crear una cadena Unicode en Python usando una &lt;code&gt;u&lt;/code&gt; delante de la cadena literal, pero esto no siempre es posible, como cuando se lee de un fichero. Para convertir entre distintas codificaciones existe la funcin &lt;code&gt;unicode&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La funcin &lt;code&gt;unicode&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;no utiliza UTF&amp;ndash;8 por defecto&lt;/strong&gt;, sino, absurdamente, ASCII. Por eso &lt;em&gt;slo es equivalente a poner una &lt;code&gt;u&lt;/code&gt; delante una cadena si se especifica que el &lt;code&gt;encoding&lt;/code&gt; sea &lt;code&gt;'utf-8'&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: python"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;unicode_string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;u"Aos"&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;unicode_str&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;unicode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;some.txt&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;r&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;read&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;encoding&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;utf-8&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">py2app excludes</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2013/12/02/py2app-excludes/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2013-12-02-py2app-excludes</id>
  <published>2013-12-02T20:58:08Z</published>
  <updated>2013-12-02T20:58:08Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al generar una aplicacin para Mac OS X con py2app, a menudo se generan ejecutables muy pesados, por ejemplo 20 MBs para una aplicacin de lnea de comandos (!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uno de los problemas es que py2app tiende a incluir muchos mdulos de la librera estndar de Python que en realidad no hacen falta. Se pueden excluir especficamente incluyndolos en la opcin excludes que se pasa a la funcin setup en el archivo setup.py usado para generar la aplicacin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Con la lista siguiente, el peso baja de 22 MBs a 6 MBs. Probablemente se puede rebajar an ms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: python"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# File: setup.py&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;setuptools&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;APP&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;path/main.py&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Plist&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;DATA_FILES&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;OPTIONS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;argv_emulation&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class="c1"&gt;#&amp;#39;iconfile&amp;#39;: &amp;#39;Icons/ConverterIcon.icns&amp;#39;,&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;plist&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Plist&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;excludes&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;aetypes&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;ast&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;bz2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;calendar&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;codecs&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;collections&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;ctypes&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;distutils&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;doctest&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;email&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;encodings&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;functools&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;gzip&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;inspect&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;itertools&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;locale&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;logging&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;optparse&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;pickle&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;platform&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;pprint&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;random&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;re&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;sets&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;shutil&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;socket&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;ssl&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;subprocess&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;tarfile&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;tempfile&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;threading&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;traceback&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;types&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;unittest&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;urllib&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;urllib2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;urlparse&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;weakref&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;xml&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
               &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;zipfile&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
           &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;app&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;APP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;package_dir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;src&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# you may not need this&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;data_files&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;DATA_FILES&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"0.1"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;description&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&amp;lt;Your description&amp;gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;author&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&amp;lt;Your name&amp;gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;author_email&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&amp;lt;Your email&amp;gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;options&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;py2app&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;OPTIONS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;setup_requires&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;py2app&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Compilar Cython</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2013/11/19/compilar-cython/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2013-11-19-compilar-cython</id>
  <published>2013-11-19T08:30:14Z</published>
  <updated>2013-11-19T08:30:14Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compilar ficheros de Cython es ms fcil usando la funcin &lt;code&gt;cythonize&lt;/code&gt; dentro del setup.py de nuestro proyecto:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: python"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# File: setup.py&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;distutils.core&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;Cython.Build&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cythonize&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"My hello app"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;ext_modules&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cythonize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;fibonacci.pyx&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# accepts a glob pattern&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por ejemplo, el fichero a compilar es fibonacci.pyx, que contiene un ejemplo del tutorial de Cython:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: python"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# File: fibonacci.pyx&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;fib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El resultado de compilar &lt;code&gt;fibonacci.pyx&lt;/code&gt; es un fichero con cdigo intermedio en C &lt;code&gt;fibonacci.c&lt;/code&gt; y un fichero compilado &lt;code&gt;fibonacci.so&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: bash"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ python setup.py build
running build
running build_ext
building &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;fibonacci&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; extension
/usr/bin/clang ...snip... -o build/lib.macosx-10.8-x86_64-2.7/fibonacci.so
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;El compilador que se utiliza es el que sea por defecto del sistema en ese momento. An estoy investigando cmo seleccionar un compilador en concreto, o aadir libreras y flags.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El fichero .so puede usarse desde otros mdulos de Python, o directamente desde la shell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: pycon"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;fibonacci&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;fibonacci&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;fib&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;1 1 2 3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Infraestructura de lanzamientos locales</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://logc.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/infraestructura-de-lanzamientos-locales/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-logc-github-io:-blog-2013-11-17-infraestructura-de-lanzamientos-locales</id>
  <published>2013-11-17T21:43:12Z</published>
  <updated>2013-11-17T21:43:12Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>logc</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este post describe cmo crear una infraestructura de lanzamientos locales, para compartir paquetes locales con otros desarrolladores del mismo equipo, basndose en Python y Macports. Esto presupone que los otros miembros del equipo usan todos Mac OS X, y que estn interesados en usar paquetes de Python, claro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Necesitaremos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;crear un paquete de Python con su correspondiente &lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;tener un directorio &lt;code&gt;releases&lt;/code&gt; servido por HTTP por el servidor Apache  integrado en el sistema operativo.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;tener un directorio &lt;code&gt;ports&lt;/code&gt; servido por rsync.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;configurar Macports para usar este nuevo repositorio.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id="crear-un-paquete-de-ejemplo-en-python"&gt;Crear un paquete de ejemplo en Python&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crea un directorio llamado &lt;code&gt;pyhello&lt;/code&gt;, y los siguientes directorios y ficheros dentro de l:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt; pyhello&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;  __init__.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;  main.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt; setup.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El contenido de &lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: python"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;setuptools&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;setup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;pyhello&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;version&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;0.1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;packages&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;pyhello&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="n"&gt;entry_points&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;console_scripts&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;pyhello=pyhello.main:main&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]})&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El contenido de &lt;code&gt;pyhello/main.py&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: python"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"Hello from pyhello!"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despus crea una distribucin de fuentes con el comando estndar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;python setup.py sdist&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esto crea un lanzamiento llamado &lt;code&gt;pyhello-0.1.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt; bajo el directorio &lt;code&gt;dist&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="servir-lanzamientos-por-http"&gt;Servir lanzamientos por HTTP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crea un directorio &lt;code&gt;releases&lt;/code&gt; bajo &lt;code&gt;~/Sites&lt;/code&gt;. Copia el fichero &lt;code&gt;dist/pyhello-0.1.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt; all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crea un fichero de configuracin para Apache en &lt;code&gt;/etc/apache2/users/YOUR_USERNAME.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El contenido de &lt;code&gt;YOUR_USERNAME.conf&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: apacheconf"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;Directory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"/Users/YOUR_USERNAME/Sites/"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;Options&lt;/span&gt; Indexes Multiviews
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;AllowOverride&lt;/span&gt; AuthConfig Limit
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;Order&lt;/span&gt; allow,deny
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;Allow&lt;/span&gt; from &lt;span class="k"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/Directory&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para lanzar Apache slo durante esta sesin de la mquina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; sudo apachectl start
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para lanzar Apache automticamente cada vez que se inicia la mquina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; sudo launchctl load -w /System/Library/LaunchDaemons/org.apache.httpd.plist
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="crear-un-fichero-portfile"&gt;Crear un fichero Portfile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El contenido de un fichero Portfile para un proyecto de Python normal (basado en un &lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt;) es:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# -*- coding: utf-8; mode: tcl; tab-width: 4; truncate-lines: t; indent-tabs-mode: nil; c-basic-offset: 4 -*- vim:fenc=utf-8:et:sw=4:ts=4:sts=4
# $Id$

PortSystem 1.0
PortGroup python 1.0

name                py-pyhello
version             0.1

categories-append   devel
license             BSD
maintainers         your.mail.provider.com:your.mail.name
description         An example Python app
long_description    Pyhello is an example Python app, distributed over \
                    local Macports

platforms           darwin
supported_archs     noarch

homepage            http://your.local.machine/~YOUR_USERNAME/
master_sites        http://your.local.machine/~YOUR_USERNAME/releases/
distname            pyhello-${version}

python.versions     26 27

checksums           rmd160 b8a9e7e5db29d407db95310ee95e7048d6fa1cdd \
                    sha256 cd8693792f5e6632c0c7efd287b5153571173cc3a26f98c2cead7af6a0445b2b&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aclaraciones&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;PortGroup&lt;/code&gt; para python configura los comandos de &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; e &lt;code&gt;install&lt;/code&gt;;  tambin existen grupos para &lt;code&gt;haskell&lt;/code&gt; y otros.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;el nombre del paquete es manipulado para generar un paquete por cada versin  listada en &lt;code&gt;python.versions&lt;/code&gt;. En este ejemplo, se generaran &lt;code&gt;py26-pyhello&lt;/code&gt; y  &lt;code&gt;py27-pyhello&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;la convencin para el campo &lt;code&gt;maintainers&lt;/code&gt; es &lt;code&gt;gmail.com:user&lt;/code&gt; para  &lt;code&gt;user@gmail.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;para generar los digests del lanzamiento con los siguientes comandos:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; openssl sha256 dist/pyhello-0.1.tar.gz
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; openssl rmd160 dist/pyhello-0.1.tar.gz
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="servir-portfiles-por-rsync"&gt;Servir Portfiles por rsync&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crea un directorio &lt;code&gt;ports&lt;/code&gt; bajo &lt;code&gt;~/Sites&lt;/code&gt;, y los siguentes subdirectorios en l:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt; python&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;     pyhello&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;         Portfile&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copia el fichero Portfile a su ubicacin mostrada y ejecuta el siguiente comando en el directorio &lt;code&gt;ports&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; portindex
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Creating port index in ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Adding port python/pyhello&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Adding subport py26-pyhello&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Adding subport py27-pyhello&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="go"&gt;Total number of ports parsed:	3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Ports successfully parsed:	3&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Ports failed:			0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Up-to-date ports skipped:	0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aunque rsync viene instalado por defecto, usaremos la versin instalada con Macports en lo siguiente. La versin por defecto est en &lt;code&gt;/usr/bin&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crear un fichero para &lt;code&gt;launchctl&lt;/code&gt; en &lt;code&gt;/Library/LaunchDaemons/name.YOUR_USERNAME.rsync.plist&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El contenido de &lt;code&gt;rsync.plit&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: xml"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="cp"&gt;&amp;lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="cp"&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE plist PUBLIC "-//Apple Computer//DTD PLIST 1.0//EN" "http://www.apple.com/DTDs/PropertyList-1.0.dtd"&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;plist&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;version=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;"1.0"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;dict&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Disabled&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;false/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Label&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;name.YOUR_USERNAME.rsync&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Program&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;/opt/local/bin/rsync&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;ProgramArguments&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;array&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;/opt/local/bin/rsync&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;--daemon&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;--config=/opt/local/etc/rsyncd.conf&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/array&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;inetdCompatibility&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;dict&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Wait&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;false/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/dict&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Sockets&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;dict&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Listeners&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;dict&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;SockServiceName&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;rsync&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;SockType&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/key&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;stream&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/string&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/dict&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/dict&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/dict&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/plist&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El contenido de &lt;code&gt;/opt/local/etc/rsyncd.conf&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: ini"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;[ports]&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="na"&gt;path&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;/Users/YOUR_USERNAME/Sites/ports&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;log file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;/opt/local/var/log/rsyncd.log&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;pid file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;/opt/local/var/run/rsyncd.pid&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;read only&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aadir rsync a &lt;code&gt;launchctl&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; sudo launchctl load -w /Library/LaunchDaemons/name.YOUR_USERNAME.rsync.plist
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comprueba que slo se pueden listar los ports y nada ms del sistema de fichero:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; rsync -axv rsync://localhost/
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; rsync -axv rsync://localhost/ports/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id="configurar-macports"&gt;Configurar Macports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Configura Macports en todas las mquinas que deban poder acceder a los nuevos paquetes. El nuevo repositorio debe ir antes del repositorio por defecto para evitar conflictos de nombres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;rsync://localhost/ports/
rsync://rsync.macports.org/release/ports/ [default]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comprueba desde otras mquinas que se pueden encontrar los nuevos paquetes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; port search pyhello
&lt;span class="go"&gt;py-pyhello @0.1 (python, devel)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;    An example Python app&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="go"&gt;py26-pyhello @0.1 (python, devel)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;    An example Python app&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="go"&gt;py27-pyhello @0.1 (python, devel)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;    An example Python app&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despus de instalar el nuevo paquete, sus comandos estn a nuestra disposicin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: console"&gt;
 &lt;div class="source"&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; sudo port install py27-pyhello
&lt;span class="gp"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt; pyhello
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Hello from pyhello!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry></feed>